# Edgar Orlando Castro Méndez

Call: +1 (202) 938-6656

Email: ecastrom71@gmail.com

### SUMMARY

Ph.D. candidate in Economics from George Mason University with a robust foundation in Applied Microeconomics, Experimental Economics, and Public Economics. Edgar possesses over 5 years of professional experience with the Inter-American Development Bank, complemented by academia roles at George Mason and Universidad de los Andes. His significant contributions in public economics research are underscored by his work on public policy.

### METHODS:

Advanced applied econometrics, experimental design, causal inference, impact evaluation, applied microeconomic theory.

### **EDUCATION**

- PhD in Economics, George Mason University, Fairfax, Virginia, (Expected: Spring 2024)
- M.A in Economics, Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia, August 2013.
- B.A in Economics, Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá, Colombia, March 2012.

# **RESEARCH INTERESTS**

 Applied Microeconomics, Experimental Economics, Public Economics and Political Economy

# **PUBLICATIONS**

 Carrillo, P. E., Castro, E., and Scartascini, C. (2021). Public good provision and property tax compliance: Evidence from a natural experiment. Journal of Public Economics, 198:104422. <u>Download</u>

# WORK EXPERIENCE

- Graduate Research Assistant, George Mason University, Virginia, August 2017 present
- Consultant, Inter-American Development Bank, Washington, DC, March 2022 December 2023. (IFD/FMM)
- Consultant, Inter-American Development Bank, Washington, DC, October 2021 November 2021. (RES)
- Pre-doctoral fellow, CESED, Universidad de los Andes, Bogotá August 2018 May 2019.
- Consultant, Inter-American Development Bank, Washington, DC, May 2018 October 2018.
- Research Fellow, Inter-American Development Bank, Washington, DC, September 2014
  August 2017. (RES)

- External Consultant, SENA, Bogota, Colombia, January 2014 July 2014.
- Researcher, ECON ESTUDIO, Bogota, Colombia, December 2011 January 2014.
- Intern, ECON ESTUDIO, Bogotá, Colombia, January 2011 August 2011.

#### TEACHING EXPERIENCE

- Teaching Assistant, Game theory for Ph.D., George Mason University, (Spring 2021 Fall 2022)
- Teaching Assistant, Applied Econometrics, George Mason University, Spring 2021.
- Teaching Assistant, Microeconomics for graduates, George Mason University, Spring 2020m Spring 2021.
- Teaching Assistant, Introduction to Microeconomics for undergraduates, Universidad de los Andes, Fall 2013 and Spring 2014.
- Teaching Assistant, Regulation and Competition Policy for graduates, Universidad de los Andes, Fall 2012 and Spring 2013.

# **WORK IN PROGRESS**

- Dissertation project: *Three essays on public economics and market interventions.* Chair: Cesar Martinelli. Committee: Thomas Stratmann, Daniel Houser.
- "Hoarding and Price Restrictions" (with Cesar Martinelli)
- "How does flexibilization of public procurement affect its efficiency?" (with Anastasya Yarygina Udovenko)
- "Patronage Networks and Favoritism in Colombian Public Procurement" (with Hugo Diaz)
- "Collective Deliberation: Theory and Experiment" (with Mikhail Freer and Cesar Martinelli)
- Castro, E and Scartascini, C (2019), Imperfect Attention in Public Policy: A Field Experiment during a Tax Amnesty in Argentina. <u>Download</u>

# RESEARCH AND CONSULTING

- Is the Colombian public services' subsidy focalization system an electoral manipulation scheme? M.A. Thesis. Manuscript, Universidad de los Andes. June 2013.
- Differentiation of Financial Institutions for Risk Deposit Insurance, Guide for methodological validation. September 2013.

### OTHER RELEVANT EXPERIENCE

 Design and Formulation of Electricity Demand Subsidies in Colombia [Spanish]: Background paper for the Energy Transformation Mission. By Marcela Eslava and Miguel Revolo. 2020

- The Legacies of Civil War on Citizens' Preferences for Democracy and the Rule of Law: Co-authored with Ana Arjona (Northwestern U.), Juan C. Cardenas (Uniandes), Ana M. Ibañez (Uniandes), and Patricia Justino (IDS).
- Commitment to Equity Assessment (CEQ), Colombian Chapter: Authored by Nora Lustig and Marcela Meléndez, 2013.
- Public Development Banks and Access to Credit in Colombia: A study by Marcela Eslava, Marcela Meléndez, and Alessandro Maffioli, conducted between 2012 and 2013.
- Labor Productivity in Colombia: Authored by Marcela Meléndez for The World Bank, 2013.
- Formalization Policy Experiments: Co-authored with Sebastian Galiani, funded by IDB-MAP in 2013.
- The Liquid Fuels Industry in Colombia [Spanish]: A collaborative project for the Colombian Association of Oil Companies (ACP) by Carlos Caballero, Marcela Meléndez, and Ricardo Paredes, between 2012 and 2013.
- Natural Gas Competitiveness in Colombia [Spanish]: Commissioned by Naturgas in 2012, with contributions from Alberto Brugman, Marcela Meléndez, Guillermo Perry, and Pablo Roda.
- Content Production for <u>www.visioneconomica.com</u>: Carried out under the guidance of Mariana Martínez and Marcela Meléndez from January 2011 to August 2011.
- The Textile/Apparel Sector in Colombia [Spanish]: A 2011 project for INEXMODA by Marcela Meléndez and María José Uribe.
- Baseline Design and Analysis for "Hogar Digital" [Spanish]: Authored by Raquel Bernal and Marcela Meléndez in 2011, for the Ministry of Technologies and Communications of Colombia.

# **CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS**

- National Tax Association, annual meeting, Tampa, Florida, 2019.
- The Association of Private Enterprise Education, annual meeting, Fort Lauderdale, Florida, 2021.
- The Association of Private Enterprise Education, annual meeting, Las Vegas, Nevada, 2022.
- The Shadow Economy, Tax Behavior, and Institutions, Brunel University London, Warsaw University, Online, 2021

# **GRANTS AND AWARDS**

- Graduate Research Assistant scholarship, ICES, George Mason University, 2017present
- Undergraduate Full Scholarship "Quiero Estudiar", Universidad de los Andes, 2007-2011.
- Best Standardized Test Score for college admission Ranking: first place ("Mejores ICFES 2006").

### **OTHERS**

- Stata, R, Python, Otree
- Spanish (native), English (fluent)